Guide to the Stanford Technology Ventures Program, Entrepreneurial Thought Leaders Seminar, Videorecordings SC1209
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Videorecordings, 2001-2014
  - Orr, Dominic, Differences between Going Public in the Dot-com and Post Dot-com Eras, 2007-10-17; 1865; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Orr, Dominic, CEO of Aruba Networks, observes a significant difference between going public in the post dot-com boom era in comparison to the actual boom. Orr argues that in the post-bubble era investors are much more thoughtful and analytical.
  - Orr, Dominic, Private versus Public Company Tradeoffs: Building Credibility, 2007-10-17; 1866; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Orr, Dominic, CEO of Aruba Networks, describes the tradeoffs for an entrepreneurial company between being private or public. Orr argues that being public offers a significant benefit for an entrepreneurial company because it confers credibility and legitimacy which can aid the startup in selling to larger organizations. Of course, these benefits must be weighed against the costs and limitations imposed by being a public company.
  - Orr, Dominic, Seeking Advice and Guidance as a CEO, 2007-10-17; 1867; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Orr, Dominic, CEO of Aruba Networks, reflects on sources of advice and guidance in his role as CEO. Orr highlights the importance of a rigorous board and advisors to challenge his thinking. However, Orr also speaks about his use of psychological counselors to help his executive team work together as effectively as possible. He suggests that this effort is vital because although there are many talented individuals in Silicon Valley, helping these individuals work together as a team is the most important element required for success.
  - Orr, Dominic, Working With and Making Decisions with Great People, 2007-10-17; 1868; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Orr, Dominic, CEO of Aruba Networks, begins by describing two surprises he encountered when working with great people: first, how difficult it is for experienced people to change and second, how challenging it is to be intellectually honest. Orr then describes his efforts to overcome these impediments by cultivating a fast-decision making process focused on the facts and intellectual honesty. However, to achieve this environment each individual has to have a thick-skin and a commitment to self-evaluation, qualities that usually must be cultivated over time.
  - Orr, Dominic, Work-Life Balance for Driven People, 2007-10-17; 1869; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Orr, Dominic, CEO of Aruba Networks, wrestles with the definition of work-life balance for people deeply engaged by their work. Orr recognizes it can be difficult to separate work and life, but that we must still make room for relationships that matter to us. According to Orr, this ultimately comes down to carefully allocating our time and energy.
  - Orr, Dominic, Silicon Valley Compared to the World, 2007-10-17; 1870; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Orr, Dominic, CEO of Aruba Networks, compares Silicon Valley to other places in the world and argues there are many more similarities than differences. Indeed, Orr emphasizes only one difference between Silicon Valley and the rest of the world: a focus on speed. By contrast, Orr argues that there are many similarities, namely how hard people work. He suggests that people work so hard for three reasons: 1) People want to have an impact, 2) People want to be in an environment they enjoy and 3) People want to be rewarded and recognized. The key to motivating people then, is allowing them to obtain these three objectives.
  - Orr, Dominic, Differences between Student Life and Professional Life, 2007-10-17; 1871; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Orr, Dominic, CEO of Aruba Networks, reflects on what he wished he had known as a student. Orr argues that as a student, a great deal of emphasis was placed on individual accomplishment whereas in professional life the accomplishments of the team and the company are much more important than any individual contribution.
  - Orr, Dominic, Challenges in Cracking Big Markets, 2007-10-17; 1872; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Orr, Dominic, CEO of Aruba Networks, responds to a question about whether startups have a chance of cracking markets owned by big competitors. Orr suggests that startups often can find niches in big markets because they have greater speed to execution. However, Orr argues that success in a big market may be more than simply creating a niche but rather success is creating a large, sustainable business. Orr argues that the challenge of creating a large business is that you attract the attention of large competitors who try to destroy you. At the same time, as a company grows, it too eventually becomes vulnerable to smaller startups with even greater relative speed to execution.
  - Orr, Dominic, Selling High-Tech Products and Services to an Executive Team, 2007-10-17; 1873; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Orr, Dominic, CEO of Aruba Networks, argues that to sell a technical product to an executive team, an entrepreneurial firm must focus on understanding and eliminating that executive team's problems. Eliminating CEO, CIO, CTO or CFOs problems means understanding and addressing their pain point sufficiently to overcome their fear of something new.
  - Orr, Dominic, Lessons from Applying the HP Way to Startups, 2007-10-17; 1874; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Orr, Dominic, CEO of Aruba Networks, speaks about lessons learned from applying the HP way to startups. Orr suggests that he has achieved great results from giving employees respect and dignity. At the same time, Orr acknowledges mistakes he has made in applying the HP way to startups. In particular, in a large organization, such as HP, there time for long feedback cycles because any mistakes from giving people too much benefit of the doubt are covered by the overall inertia of large company. By contrast, in a startup, there is little inertia and so the feedback cycle must be shorter and mistakes or problems must be resolved quickly.
  - Orr, Dominic, The Benefits of Advanced Technical Training, 2007-10-17; 1875; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Orr, Dominic, CEO of Aruba Networks, argues that the unique benefit of advanced technical training is not necessarily analytical thinking--this skill can be developed in many places. Rather Orr suggests that the benefit of advanced technical training is the courage to address uncertain problems with brutal intellectual honesty. For Orr, this quality has allowed him to innovate on the technical frontier while having the courage to recognize when he might have failed and needed to redirect his efforts.
  - Christensen, Stan, Negotiations are Serial Events, 2007-10-31; 1876; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Christensen, Stan highlights the fact that negotiations are serial events. He notes that it is important for one to realize this as you would encounter the same people in the future. He illustrates this fact from his experience in Seoul.
  - Christensen, Stan, What is Effective Negotiation?, 2007-10-31; 1877; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Christensen, Stan throws light on the art of effective negotiation. He defines it as any attempt to persuade or influence a party to do something. He adds a note of humor by illustrating it with a story of one his students.
  - Christensen, Stan, Communication and Negotiation, 2007-10-31; 1878; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Christensen, Stan believes that communication is a key element in negotiation. He stresses the fact that communication is about convincing the other side that you can hear them and that they are being heard. He illustrates it with anecdotes and his personal experiences in negotiating deals.
  - Christensen, Stan, Negotiating Salaries, 2007-10-31; 1879; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Christensen, Stan talks about his experience in negotiating salaries and fills the conversation with interesting personal experiences. He believes that developing a best alternative to a negotiated agreement and having a good idea about the objective criteria is key to effective negotiation of salaries.
  - Bawden, Larry, Switching To Solar Energy, 2007-11-07; 1881; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bawden, Larry talks about the switch from Hydrogen to Solar Energy. He addresses the immense potential in Solar Energy. Bawden notes that this spaces has a very high investment rate in the past and believes that solar is a clean way to convert electricity.
  - Bawden, Larry, Challenges in Manufacturing Solar Energy, 2007-11-07; 1882; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bawden, Larry addresses the challenges in producing Solar Energy on a commercial scale. He highlights the capital intensive requirements in this field. He also notes the importance of precise nano-engineering in the manufacturing process.
  - Bawden, Larry, Channeling Solar Energy Demand, 2007-11-07; 1883; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bawden, Larry discusses the immense potential in Solar Energy by illustrating the high demand for this alternative source. He notes that there is huge demand from a variety of sources - residential houses to large industries. He also highlights the fact that substantial demand for this energy source is international.
  - Berjikly, Armen, Delivering Shared Experiences, 2007-11-14; 1884; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Armen Berjikly, Founder and CEO of Experience Project, shares the basic concept behind the company: a portal for people to share experiences with others in a similar situation. He illustrates by giving an example of a young mother diagnosed with breast cancer. He notes that his portal offered her an opportunity to talk to people who had similar experiences and thereby making her journey less painful.
  - Bawden, Larry, Competitive Strategy for Solar Energy Start-ups, 2007-11-07; 1885; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Bawden, Larry discusses the competitive strategy in solar energy start-ups lies in bringing vertical integration to your product mix. He believes that there is a huge potential for any viable technology in the value chain. He notes that continuous improvement of technology is key to the success of a company in this field.
  - Berjikly, Armen, Transitioning from Corporate to Startup, 2007-11-14; 1886; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Armen Berjikly, Founder and CEO of Experience Project, discusses his transition from corporate life to founding his own company. Berjikly talks about the challenges of bootstrapping his company: dealing with the loss of stable income, juggling jobs to make ends meet, and developing the alpha product.
  - Berjikly, Armen, Hiring For a Startup, 2007-11-14; 1887; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Armen Berjikly, Founder and CEO of Experience Project, discusses how to build a start-up team, a task that he argues is critical for success. Berjikly suggests building a team of people with complementary skills by reaching out through personal networks and in some cases recruiters. On the other hand, he suggests that entrepreneurs avoid hiring from sites such as Craigslist or other sources where it is difficult to verify someone's skills.
  - Berjikly, Armen, Marketing Strategies for a Startup Website, 2007-11-14; 1888; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Armen Berjikly, Founder and CEO of Experience Project, talks about different strategies to market a startup, particularly an Internet startup. Berjikly suggests linking to larger sites by building on open platforms such as Myspace and Facebook as well as finding your way into social identification tools such as Digg and StumbleUpon.
  - Navin, Ashwin, Founding Teams, 2007-11-28; 1889; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Ashwin Navin, Co-founder and President of Bit Torrent, talks about founding teams--where they come from and how to form them. Navin suggests that founding teams emerge from relationships developed in school or work and that founding teams work best when the team members have complementary skills. In addition, Navin emphasizes the quality of students and colleagues in Silicon Valley and suggests that students take the opportunity to experiment with new business opportunities.
  - Navin, Ashwin, Stages of a Startup, 2007-11-28; 1890; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Ashwin Navin, Co-founder and President of Bit Torrent, alludes to a theory by Bob Cringely about the three stages of a company - Commandos, Infantry and Military Police. Navin suggests that startup success relies on successfully identifying and executing on the demands of each phase, as well as transitioning between phases, by bringing in the right team members for each stage of the company.
  - Navin, Ashwin, Why Investors Invest: Bit Torrent as an Example, 2007-11-28; 1891; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Ping Li, Partner at Accel, talks about how they evaluated Bit Torrent as a potential venture capital investment. Li suggests that Bit Torrent possessed three things which led to the eventual investment: 1) Deep, distinctive technology and a really meaningful problem, 2) A strong team that had proved a legitimate business model and 3) Shared vision about the future potential of the company.
  - Navin, Ashwin, The Value of an Open Source Model, 2007-11-28; 1892; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Ping Li, Partner at Accel, argues that open source can be an effective business model for some startups although not all startups. Li argues that the key value of an open source model is not the collective input of a broad contributor base--the reality is that the application creator almost always puts in a great deal more effort creating the application than the community. Rather, the value of an open source model is free distribution across a broad base of contributors and users without costly sales forces or overhead. However, monetization of an open source model is a little different as it requires offering optional value-add features that users may want.
  - Jordan, Rodrigo, The Accelerating Pace of Change, 2007-05-03; 1893; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Jordan, Rodrigo, Founder of Vertical, suggests that technology and paradigms are changing at an accelerating pace. Because of this, what made one successful in the past may not lead to success in the future. Therefore, Jordan argues that entrepreneurship is a way of life in which on engages and tries to stay ahead of change over the course of your life.
  - Jordan, Rodrigo, Optimism in Overcoming Challenges, 2007-05-03; 1894; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Jordan, Rodrigo, Founder of Vertical, describes a challenge in making the first crossing of the Ellsworth Mountains in Antarctica, highlighting the role in optimism in allowing the team to shift their paradigm and successfully cross an ice valley. Jordan then argues that the entrepreneurs he admires have a similar, paradigm shifting optimism: despite the challenges and disappointments that his colleagues inevitably face, these entrepreneurs overcome their challenges with optimism.
  - Khanna, Tarun, Entrepreneurship Is Social Entrepreneurship, 2007-05-03; 1895; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khanna, Tarun, Professor at Harvard Business School, speaks about the incredible change in aspirations among young people in India. Whereas in the past young people aspired to become government officials, today they aspire to become entrepreneurs and lift themselves out of poverty by their own actions. Khanna reflects that this change in attitudes is inspiring and very good for the country.
  - Khanna, Tarun, Comparing Development in India and China, 2007-05-03; 1896; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khanna, Tarun, Professor at Harvard Business School, summarizes insights from one of his books by comparing private and public rights in India and China. Khanna argues that in India, private rights are favored over the public interest whereas in China the opposite is true. These tradeoffs affect the nature of doing business in each country and development. Elsewhere in his presentation, Khanna also suggests that India and China differ in that India has weak hard infrastructure (roads, etc.) but strong soft infrastructure (human assets, etc.) whereas in China the opposite is true, a duality that is clearly related to the public and private rights distinction discussed in this video segment.
  - Khanna, Tarun, Social Entrepreneurship in Medical Care, 2007-05-03; 1897; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khanna, Tarun, Professor at Harvard Business School, highlights the ability of entrepreneurs to provide solutions to social problems by telling the story of a cardiac hospital in India. Khanna points out that the founder, a cardiac surgeon and entrepreneur, has been able to achieve incredible results unmatched by private or public institutions around the world by rethinking the scale on which healthcare is delivered. Khanna emphasizes that this kind of entrepreneurship can solve social problems in ways that often governments cannot.
  - Khanna, Tarun, Government and Entrepreneurship: The Evolution of Entrepreneurship in China, 2007-05-03; 1898; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Khanna, Tarun, Professor at Harvard Business School, argues that the old equation that government = inefficient does not hold unilaterally but depends on the context. To illustrate, Khanna describes the evolution of the Communist Party of China and its efforts to co-opt entrepreneurs so that now the government and entrepreneurship is very closely integrated. In contrast, Khanna suggests that in India entrepreneurs keep their distance from the government.
  - Draper, Tim, Entrepreneurs Are Heroes and Change Agents, 2007-05-03; 1899; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Draper, Tim, Partner at Draper Fisher Jurvetson, suggests that entrepreneurs are heroes because they are the real change agents in the world. Although politicians often recognize and propose programs to address problems, it is most often entrepreneurs who actually fix problems by taking big risks to achieve their vision.
  - Draper, Tim, Increasing Pace of Technical and Entrepreneurial Change, 2007-05-03; 1900; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Draper, Tim, Partner at Draper Fisher Jurvetson, argues that the pace of technical change and adoption is increasing. This increasing rate of change is driven both by a growing customer base connected to the Internet as well as the growing number of entrepreneurs who are able to participate in global markets from anywhere in the world.
  - Kapor, Mitch, Competing with Giants, 2008-01-16; 1909; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Serial entrepreneur Kapor, Mitch encourages start-ups not to compete with giants. Instead, the young upstart should consider how it could benefit by working in concert with their giant's footsteps. He cites as an example his own young enterprise, Foxmarks, which tracks search trends through the amalgamation of Firefox bookmarks.
  - Kapor, Mitch, A Successful Business Solves Problems, 2008-01-16; 1910; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    A solid business model can't survive long-term if it just draws traffic. Serial entrepreneur Kapor, Mitch points out that a concrete business plan must truly offer a solution to a well-worn market conundrum. While a flash-in-the-pan Facebook app may draw millions of users in minutes, without staying power it's not viable long term.
  - Kapor, Mitch, Disadvantages of Venture Capital, 2008-01-16; 1911; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    While entrepreneur and former Lotus 1-2-3 founder Kapor, Mitch understands how selling finance can boost a burgeoning enterprise, his experience has also acquainted him with some of the disadvantages - mainly accountability and a forced schedule of progress. Here, Kapor outlines some of the many alternatives to the traditional VC paradigm, including self-financing and angel funding.
  - Kapor, Mitch, Choosing an Investor, 2008-01-16; 1912; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Selecting a financial partner for your growing enterprise should be as careful a process as selecting a member of your senior staff, says serial entrepreneur Kapor, Mitch. Here he discusses why real start-ups offering real opportunity can afford to be choosy.
  - Kapor, Mitch, The Great Talent Vacuum Cleaner, 2008-01-16; 1913; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Former Lotus 1-2-3 founder Kapor, Mitch has launched a number of new ventures, and he knows firsthand the difficulty of competing with the Valley's best-known brands for top engineering and executive talent. He shares his solutions to luring the best in human resources to his door, including distributed development and opening doors elsewhere in the Golden Gate.
  - Kapor, Mitch, The Value of Company Culture, 2008-01-16; 1914; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Former Lotus 1-2-3 founder Kapor, Mitch speaks candidly about the most valuable legacy of his wildly successful 1980's technology company: the management of free-thinking creatives. He stands by the quality of his products, but it was his huge investment in human resources, Libertarian management style, and incentives toward great job satisfaction and accountability that he's most proud of. He claims that the thousands of Lotus alumni have helped set the standard for how tech companies are managed on the East Coast and beyond.
  - Kapor, Mitch, Social Responsibility from the Ground Up, 2008-01-16; 1915; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Social entrepreneur Kapor, Mitch believes that social responsibility must be integrated into the organization, and not just the frosting on the cake.
  - Kapor, Mitch, Balancing Information Asymmetry for the Entrepreneur, 2008-01-16; 1916; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Kapor, Mitch has been an entrepreneur since the 1980's, and here he pinpoints useful websites, educational programs, and learning opportunities that help level the playing field between seasoned venture capitalist and the first-time business operator.
  - Conway, Ron, Flying with Angel Investors, 2008-01-23; 1917; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Taking its name from the early investors of classic Hollywood, Ron Conway and Mike Maples define the angel investor. In addition, they explain the differences between angel investors and venture capitalists, and point out why an angel's smaller dollars might be a better choice, as they're often paired with a broader range of exit strategies and tools to keep start-ups in business.
  - Conway, Ron, A Match Made in Heaven? Your Angel Investor and You, 2008-01-23; 1918; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    How should an aspiring entrepreneur choose an angel investor? And, more importantly, how will an angel investor select you? Entrepreneurs need to gain access to the right angel - one that will add value to their growing enterprise. The top angels in the business, says investor Mike Maples, are seeking ideas that have been tested for market viability - an essential criteria before they'll consider cutting a check.
  - Conway, Ron, What Does an Angel Investor Do?, 2008-01-23; 1919; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    Investors Mike Maples and Ron Conway explain their job like this: They help all lights turn green for the fast-moving car of the Internet start-up. In addition to cutting a check, these angel investors explain the panoramic view of what a good investor offers, including bringing in the right talent and business sensibilities, and building and testing product prototypes.
  - Conway, Ron, Attrition Rates for Potential Investors, 2008-01-23; 1920; 1 computer file(s) (mp4)
    The numbers are stacked against the inspired business owner-to-be. Seasoned angel investors Ron Conway and Mike Maples talk about how many ideas they receive, how many executive summaries they peruse, how many meetings they call, and the shockingly few ventures - roughly one out of 150 - that end up receiving their investment of time and money. Also, Conway points out that investing is a risky business, with an even split between those that fail, those that earn just enough to pay back their investors, and those that turn a profit.